SARANSH CHOPRA

🕏 saransh-cpp.github.io | 🗖 saransh0701@gmail.com | 🛅 saransh-cpp | 🖸 Saransh-cpp | 🏚 Blogs

About

Saransh is an engineering junior who, by day, works on his academic and professional commitments, and by night, develops and maintains Open-Source Software, which he believes are the key to an open and collaborative Software Development ecosystem.

He is passionate about Software Development, DevOps, Research Software Engineering, Machine Learning, Scientific Machine Learning, and Open-Source Software.

Education

Cluster Innovation Centre, University of Delhi

New Delhi, India

 ${\it Major: Information \ Technology \ and \ Mathematical \ Innovations}$

2020 - 2024

Minor: Computational Biology

CGPA 9.40

Research and Work Experience

FluxML, The Julia Programming Language

Remote

Technical Wroter and Open-Source Developer [Funded by The Julia Programming Language] May 2022 – November 2022 Mr. Dhairya Gandhi (Julia Computing)

- Worked on FluxML, an ML ecosystem providing lightweight abstractions on top of Julia's native GPU and AD support.
- Fixed bugs and developed the infrastructure of numerous ML packages such as Flux.jl, NNlib.jl and Metalhead.jl.
- Wrote original Machine Learning/Deep Learning tutorials, documentation and API references for FluxML's ecosystem.

Institute for Research and Innovation in Software for High Energy Physics (IRIS-HEP), Princeton University

Remote

Research and Development Fellow [Funded by IRIS-HEP]

June 2022 - October 2022

Dr. Henry Schreiner (Princeton University / CERN) and Dr. Jim Pivarski (Princeton University)

- Prepared Vector for v0.9.0, v0.10.0, and v1.0.0 (first major release) by developing new public API, fixing bugs, and building new infrastructure.
- The releases are currently being used by researchers at CERN, Princeton University, and other research institutes to construct 4D jagged (awkward) vectors and perform Just-In-Time compiled vector operations in Python.
- Worked closely with CERN and Princeton researchers to build infrastructures for the HEP ecosystem.

AiView

New Delhi, India

Research and Development Engineer

September 2021 - December 2021

Mr. Geetansh Saxena and Mr. Chappa Sri Vinay

- Developed end-to-end OCR and Object Detection libraries by wrapping existing software for visually impaired people.
- Built a CI/CD pipeline and a REST API for ease of integration with any existing software using FastAPI and Heroku.
- Collected a dataset of human images and their distance from a point by building a stereovision camera.

PyBaMM (Python Battery Mathematical Modelling), NumFOCUS

Remote

Google Summer of Code Student Developer [Funded by Google]

May 2021 - August 2021

Prof. Ferran Brosa Planella (University of Warwick), Dr. Valentin Sulzer (Carnegie Melon University), Dr. Robert Timms (University of Oxford)

- Built an automated Twitter Bot capable of constructing Mathematical Simulations of Batteries, including but not limited to different battery models, parameter sets, chemistries, degradation modes, and experiments.
- Developed a replying functionality to run Mathematical Simulations on command using Twitter API.
- o Created a novel CI CD infrastructure and followed a micro-services-based architecture.

Open Source Software

PyBaMM

NumFOCUS' Steering Committee Member, Maintainer, and Core Developer - 450+ stars

PyBaMM (Python Battery Mathematical Modelling) solves physics-based electrochemical DAE models by using state-of-the-art automatic differentiation and numerical solvers.

Vector

Collaborator and Core Developer - 45+ stars

Vector is a Python 3.7+ library for 2D, 3D, and Lorentz vectors, especially arrays of vectors, to solve common physics problems in a NumPy-like way.

[SSP] S. Chopra, H. Schreiner, and J. Pivarski. Vector: vector classes and utilities. DOI: 10.5281/zenodo.5942082. URL: https://github.com/scikit-hep/vector.

Flux.jl

Member (FluxML) and Core Contributor - 3,700+ stars

Flux is an elegant approach to machine learning. It's a 100% pure-Julia stack, and provides lightweight abstractions on top of Julia's native GPU and AD support. Flux makes the easy things easy while remaining fully hackable.

BattBot

Member (pybamm-team), Maintainer, and Core Developer - 10+ stars

An automated Twitter Bot that Tweets random Battery Mathematical Modeling Simulations and replies to the requested Battery Simulations.

liionpack

Member (pybamm-team), Maintainer, and Core Developer - 30+ stars

liionpack takes a 1D PyBaMM model and makes it into a pack. You can either specify the configuration e.g. 16 cells in parallel and 2 in series (16p2s) or load a netlist.

Other notable contributions

- **Zarr**: An implementation of chunked, compressed, N-dimensional arrays for Python. 4,500,000+ installs 1,000+ stars Migrated Zarr's build and packaging infrastructure to a pyproject.toml based configuration.
- **DeepXDE**: DeepXDE is a library for scientific machine learning 350,000+ installs 1,200+ stars Implemented utility functions and improved the existing examples on solving partial differential PDEs using PINNs.
- \circ Colour: Colour Science for Python 6,007,000+ installs 1,500+ stars Implemented the conversion between RGB and HCL colourspaces, along with tests and documentation.
- Scikit-HEP ecosystem: High Energy Physics in Python

 Fixed minor bugs in awkward and hist, added support for coverage in cookie, and wrote new developer pages.
- Scikits.odes: Offers extra ODE/DAE solvers; an extension to ones available in SciPy 160,000+ installs 100+ stars Debugged and fixed their build (which was failing because of setuptools) and removed support for Python 2.7-3.6.

Posters and Presentations

- [SSP22a] S. Chopra, H. Schreiner, and J. Pivarski. Compiling Awkward Lorentz vectors with Numba. 21st International Workshop on Advanced Computing and Analysis Techniques in Physics Research (ACAT). Poster (upcoming). Oct. 2022. URL: https://indi.to/45Kzq.
- [SSP22b] S. Chopra, H. Schreiner, and J. Pivarski. Constructing HEP vectors and analyzing HEP data using Vector. 5th International Workshop on Python in High Energy Physics (PyHEP). Presentation. Oct. 2022. DOI: https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.7081003. URL: https://indi.to/bPmMc.
- [S C22a] S. Chopra. Code coverage through unit tests running in sub-processes/threads: Locally and automated on GitHub. 10th Annual Conference on Python Asia-Pacific (PyCon APAC). Presentation. Sept. 2022. URL: https://tw.pycon.org/2022/en-us/conference/talk/243.
- [S C22b] S. Chopra. Code coverage through unit tests running in sub-processes/threads: Locally and automated on GitHub. 21st Annual Conference On Python Europe (EuroPython). Presentation. July 2022. URL: https://ep2022.europython.eu/session/code-coverage-through-unit-tests-running-in-sub-processes-threads-locally-and-automated-on-github.

Grants, Prizes and Achievements

• PyCon Acia-Pacific (APAC)'s grant to lead a talk virtually (NT\$3,600)

July 2022

• Shubhra Kar Linux Foundation Training Scholarship (500 recipients worldwide) for contributions to open-source research software (\$695)

June 2022

• EuroPython's travel grant to lead a talk in-person (£460)

June 2022

• PyCon Italia's travel grant to lead a workshop in-person (£400 + lodging support)

April 2022

• Faraday Institution's Collaboration Award for contributions to the PyBaMM ecosystem

 $November\ 2021$

 \circ Won the **Elastic hackathon** (out of 2500+ registrations) with a Flutter-Node-Google

May 2021

Cloud-ELK (Elasticsearch, Logstash, Kibana) based application

• Discovered an asteroid having a fixed orbit around Sun by analysing the data Pan-STARRS observatory

August 2016

Projects

releaseup [NLP, Text summarisation, spaCy, Scikit-learn, TF-IDF, Python library]

 $September\ 2022$

- Release up uses an extractive approach for generating release notes from comments and docstrings added b/w two git tags.
- The Python library has 200+ installs on PyPI, 5+ stars on GitHub, and follows best development practices.

- OCRed provides clever, simple, and intuitive wrapper functionalities for OCRing specific textual materials.
- The Python library has 2,300+ installs on PyPI, 10+ stars on GitHub, and follows best development practices.

ForMente NLP, Flutter, Dart, FastAPI, Python, Firebase, Firestore, Heroku, GitHub Actions

June 2022

- Using Natural Language Processing, ForMente lets you diagnose your feelings in the form of a secure personal diary.
- o The NLP model is deployed on Heroku using FastAPI, and the app uses Firebase and Firestore as its backend.

ChaoticEncryption.jl [Image processing, Encryption algorithms, ODEs, PRNGs, Julia package]

February 2022

- Vectorised image encryption and PRNG algorithms that runs ~40X faster than ordinary nested-for implementations.
- The Julia package has 10+ installs on JuliaHub and 28+ stars on GitHub.

PDEsWithPINNs [PDEs, PINNs, Python, DeepXDE]

January 2022

- Worked under Prof. Shobha Bagai to solve 1, 2, 3, and 4D Partial Differential Equations using Physics-Informed Neural Networks.
- Worked with Neural tangent Kernels, Multi-scale Fourier feature networks, and Spatio-temporal Multi-scale Fourier feature networks to predict high-frequency details.

SceneNet [Transfer Learning, VGG19, CNNs, Python, Flutter, Dart, FastAPI, Heroku]

December 2021

- Scenery detection through an Android application achieved by training VGG-19 on 10,000+ images belonging to 67 categories.
- Achieved 96% training accuracy, 64% cross-validation accuracy, and developed a standalone public API for the model.

PopItUp [Android, Kotlin, Firebase, Firestore, Google Sceneform SDK, Google ARCore SDK]

August 2

- o An Augmented Reality shooting game developed in native android by manually adding and editing the Sceneform SDK.
- Developed a live leaderboard using the FirestoreRecyclerView and Firestore.

MemeTastic [Flutter, Dart, NodeJS, Elasticsearch, Kibana, CI/CD, Google Cloud, Reddit API, Ngram Analyser] May 2021

- o Developed and deployed a backend service to ingest the latest meme data into Google Cloud hosted Elasticsearch.
- Created a frontend with a clean UI to fetch this data, providing an auto-complete feature to search any meme.

Position of Responsibilities, Volunteering, and Mentoring

o Member of PyBaMM's NumFOCUS steering committee.

Present

• Member of **FluxML**'s GitHub organisation.

Present

• Vector's collaborator on GitHub.

Present

- Mentored a hackashop conducted at the **5th International Workshop on Python in High** September 2022 **Energy Physics (PyHEP)**.
 - Mentored students under PyBaMM, NumFOCUS for Google Summer of Code 2022.

May 2022

• Mentored 10+ students under Codepeak 2021 on open-source application development.

December 2021

Relevant Skills

 $\textbf{Languages:} \hspace{1.5cm} \textbf{Python (proficient)} \hspace{0.1cm} | \hspace{0.1cm} \textbf{Julia (proficient)} \hspace{0.1cm} | \hspace{0.1cm} \textbf{Dart (proficient)} \hspace{0.1cm} | \hspace{0.1cm} \textbf{C/C++} \hspace{0.1cm} | \hspace{0.1cm} \textbf{JavaScript} \hspace{0.1cm}$

Frameworks/Libraries: Tensorflow | PyTorch | FluxML-Ecosystem | PyData-Ecosystem | SciML-Ecosystem | Flutter

FastAPI | NodeJS | ExpressJS | Android

Platforms and Tools Linux | Heroku | Google Cloud | Elasticsearch | Kibana | Shell Scripting | Docker | CI/CD | VCS

SQL and NoSQL Databases | GitHub Actions

Languages

Hindi (mother tongue), English (fluent), German (basic), Punjabi (conversational)